A Guide to the Henry M. Morris Papers, 1937-1999
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Henry M. Morris Papers, 1937-1999
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1994-028
5.7 cu. ft. 4 boxes; 1 folder
This collection contains papers relating to Morris's career as a hydraulic engineer and his position as director of the Institute for Creation Research. The materials date from 1937 to 1999 and include course materials (exams, notes), his M.S. thesis and Ph.D. dissertation, publications, technical reports, correspondence concerning such topics as hydraulic engineering and soil mechanics, and publications and pamphlets from the Institute of Creation Research.
Morris, Henry M.
Administrative Inforamtion
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Henry M. Morris Papers were donated to Special Collections in the fall of 1994. Institute for Creation Research materials were sent in multiple accessions between 1994 and 1999.
Biographical Note
Henry M. Morris (1918-2006) was both a hydraulic engineer and a creationist scientist. He received his undergraduate degree from Rice University (1939) and graduated from the University of Minnesota with his Ph.D. in 1950, writing his dissertation on "A New Concept of Flow in Rough Conduits." He served as professor of Hydraulic Engineering and Chairman of the Department of Civil Engineering (1957-1970) at Virginia Polytechnic Institute. Morris was also a fellow of the American Association for Advancement of Science and the American Society of Civil Engineers.
Dr. Henry M. Morris also served as the founder, President (1970-1996), and President Emeritus (1996-2006) of the Institute for Creation Research in San Diego, California. His most famous book, "The Genesis Flood," has been credited with helping revive the modern creationist movement.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains papers relating to Morris's career as a hydraulic engineer and Morris's role as director of the Institute for Creation Research. The materials date from 1937 to 1999. Divided into two series, Morris's papers consist of course materials (exams, notes), his M.S. thesis and Ph.D. dissertation, reprints, publications, technical reports, correspondence concerning such topics as hydraulic engineering and soil mechanics, and publications and pamphlets from the Institute for Creation Research.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series: Series I: Papers and Series II: Institute for Creation Research Materials.
Series I contains Morris's papers related to his career as a hydraulic engineer. This series is arranged in subject files.
Series II houses materials related to the Institute for Creation Research, of which Morris served as founder and director. This series is arranged by material type.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
The following book has been removed from the collection and has been catalogued for the rare book collection: Applied Hydraulics in Engineering by Henry M. Morris and James M. Wiggert. 2nd edition, 1972.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Faculty; Science and Technology; University Archives; Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Contents List
- Series I: Papers, 1937-1973
  - Course Syllabi - Descriptive Geometry 206 (n.d.), Engineering Drawing 2 (SIU, 1955-1956), and Dynamics I (1957), 1955-1957 (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Civil Engineering Notes (300 and 320 a), 1937-1943 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Civil Engineering 460 and Structural Engineering Notes (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Southern Illinois University Engineering School, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Syllabus of Courses, Department of Civil Engineering, Southwestern Louisiana Institute, 1952-1953 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Photographs - S.L.I. Engineering Shows (Box-folder 1-6)
  - E.C.P.D. Inspection, 1956 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Engineering Show, 1954-1956 (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Southwestern Louisiana Institute, 1956 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Hydraulic Engineering - Old Quizzes and Lab Problems, 1953-1956 (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Structural Design, 1952 (Box-folder 1-11)
  - Foundations, 1949 (Box-folder 1-12)
  - Hydrodynamics, 1947-1948 (Box-folder 1-13)
  - Highways and Airports, 1950 (Box-folder 1-14)
  - Soil Mechanics - Airports, 1950-1959 (Box-folder 1-15)
  - Civil Engineering 190 Notes, Mechanics of Similitude, 1947 (Box-folder 1-16)
  - Report - Civil Engineering 160, Hydraulics, 1946 (Box-folder 1-17)
  - Report - Civil Engineering 183, Open Channel Flow, 1946 (Box-folder 1-18)
  - Civil Engineering 192, Waterways, 1947 (Box-folder 1-19)
  - Civil Engineering 193 Problems, Hydraulic Measurements, 1947 (Box-folder 1-20)
  - Problems and Reading Assignments - Civil Engineering 191, 1947 (Box-folder 1-21)
  - Civil Engineering 160 - Applied Hydraulics (1950) & Civil Engineering 321 - Fluid Mechanics (c. 1951), 1950 - c. 1951 (Box-folder 1-22)
  - Structures Quizzes and Outlines, 1950 (Box-folder 1-23)
  - Fluid Mechanics - Outlines, Problems, etc., 1948-1949 (Box-folder 1-24)
  - Surveying (Minnesota), 1947 (Box-folder 1-25)
  - Sanitary Engineering, 1943 (Box-folder 1-26)
  - Surveying - E.S.M.W.T., 1942 (Box-folder 1-27)
  - Highway and Airport - Outlines and Quizzes, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 1-28)
  - 1943 C.E. "Theory of Simple Structures" by Shedd and Vawter, 1937-1943 (Box-folder 1-29)
  - Mechanics, 1944 (Box-folder 1-30)
  - Hydraulics - Quizzes, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 1-31)
  - Surveying - Rice, 1943-1946 (Box-folder 1-32)
  - Strength of Materials, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 1-33)
  - C.E. 420 - Soil Mechanics, 1938 (Box-folder 1-34)
  - Route Surveying Mechanics, 1942 (Box-folder 1-35)
  - C.E. 300 Problems and Miscellaneous, 1937 (Box-folder 1-36)
  - C.E. 300 Lab Reports, 1937 (Box-folder 1-37)
  - Reinforced Concrete, 1939 (Box-folder 1-38)
  - Airport Drainage Problems, 1950 (Box-folder 1-39)
  - The Pan-American Highway, undated (Box-folder 1-40)
  - Traffic and Safety Engineering, undated (Box-folder 1-41)
  - Fort Peck Dam, undated (Box-folder 1-42)
  - Mathematics, 1949 (Box-folder 1-43)
  - Education in Civil Engineering, 1957-1973 (Box-folder 1-44)
  - Computers and Automation, undated (Box-folder 1-45)
  - Old Resumes and Biographical Data, 1957-1969 (Box-folder 1-46)
  - C.E. 420 Engineering Laws, Contacts, and Specifications, c. 1954 (Box-folder 1-47)
  - C.E. 211 Surveying, 1957 (Box-folder 1-48)
  - C.E. 323 Strength of Materials, 1953 (Box-folder 1-49)
  - C.E. 222 Statics, 1955 (Box-folder 1-50)
  - C.E. 420 and C.E. 440, 1938-1939 (Box-folder 2-1)
  - C.E. 460, (1 of 2), 1938-1939 (Box-folder 2-2)
  - C.E. 460, (2 of 2), 1938-1939 (Box-folder 2-3)
  - Highway Research Board, 1969 (Box-folder 2-4)
  - Engineering Education at V.P.I. (1961); Soil Classification (1959); Annual Review of Research Activities (1968); Publications, Lectures, and Patents (1965-1968); and Publications and Theses (1969), 1959-1969 (Box-folder 2-5)
  - Hydraulic Research in the United States, 1968 (Box-folder 2-6)
  - Hydraulic Research in the United States, 1966 (Box-folder 2-7)
  - Hydraulic Research in the United States, 1965 (Box-folder 2-8)
  - "Roughness Elements (Peripheral Rings) as Energy Dissipators in Free-Surface Flow in Circular Pipes" Paper, 1971 (Box-folder 2-9)
  - "Energy Dissipation in Highway Drainage Channels" Presentation Paper, 1966 (Box-folder 2-10)
  - "Design of Roughness Elements for Energy Dissipation in Highway Drainage Chutes" Paper, 1969 (Box-folder 2-11)
  - "Tumbling Flow in Open Channels" Paper, undated (Box-folder 2-12)
  - Research Proposal - Hydraulic Effects of Boundary Roughness, Budget Proposal, and Related Correspondence, 1964 (Box-folder 2-13)
  - Research Proposals, 1962, 1963, 1967 (Box-folder 2-14)
  - Technical Proposal (1963) and Research Proposal (1962) - Hydraulic Effects of Boundary Roughness, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 2-15)
  - Water Resources Research Proposal, 1964 (Box-folder 2-16)
  - Rio Grande Canalization Bridge Project, 1940 (Box-folder 2-17)
  - Engineering Soil Classification for Residential Developments, 1959 (Box-folder 2-18)
  - Second Annual Report - Use of Large Roughness Elements for Hydraulic Energy Dissipation, 1965 (Box-folder 2-19)
  - First Annual Report - Use of Large Roughness Elements for Hydraulic Energy Dissipation, 1964 (Box-folder 2-20)
  - "A New Concept of Flow in Rough Conduits" Typed Manuscript, undated (Box-folder 2-21)
  - Probable Flow Effects Due to Proposed River Channel Construction, 1958 (Box-folder 2-22)
  - Fundamentals of Hydraulic Engineering, (Part 1), 1961 (Box-folder 2-23)
  - Fundamentals of Hydraulic Engineering, (Part 2), 1961 (Box-folder 2-24)
  - Fundamentals of Hydraulic Engineering, (Part 3), 1961 (Box-folder 2-25)
  - A New Concept of Flow in Rough Conduits - Draft Manuscript, 1950 (Box-folder 2-26)
  - Highway Research Council, 1957-1965 (Box-folder 2-27)
  - Hydraulics of Culverts Task Force, 1959-1969 (Box-folder 2-28)
  - I.B.C. Structural Design Notes, 1938-1942 (Box-folder 2-29)
  - Fluid Mechanics Commission, V.P.I Engineering College, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 2-30)
  - A.S.E.E. Applied Hydraulics Comm., 1958-1966 (Box-folder 2-31)
  - A.S.C.E. Hydraulics Division, 1965-1970 (Box-folder 2-32)
  - A.S.E.E. C.E. Division, 1960-1970 (Box-folder 2-33)
  - Khafaul/Morris Papers, 1964 (Box-folder 2-34)
  - N.S.F. Panel, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 2-35)
  - E.C.P.D. Visit - University of Missouri, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 2-36)
  - Marshall University Inspection, 1964 (Box-folder 2-37)
  - Olin-Mathieson, 1957-1960 (Box-folder 3-1, Folder 1)
  - E.C.P.D. Visit - Tennessee Tech, 1966-1970 (Box-folder 3-2)
  - Brookhaven Project, 1952-1954 (Box-folder 3-3)
  - Culvert Design Data, 1950 (Box-folder 3-4)
  - Uncompleted Culvert Flow Studies, undated (Box-folder 3-5)
  - Miscellaneous Figures - Culvert Studies, c. 1949 (Box-folder 3-6)
  - Model Culvert Studies, undated (Box-folder 3-7)
  - Large Scale Culvert Studies, undated (Box-folder 3-8)
  - Photographs - S.A.F. Hydraulics Lab, 1954 (Box-folder 3-9)
  - Hydraulic Research!!, 1962-1973 (Box-folder 3-10)
  - E. Koo Paper, 1969 (Box-folder 3-11)
  - V.P.I. Water Resources Center, 1962-1968 (Box-folder 3-12)
  - Photographs - V.P.I. Hydraulics Lab, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 3-13)
  - "Entrance Losses in Short Circular Conduits" MS Thesis Copy, 1949 (Box-folder 3-14)
  - "A New Concept of Flow in Rough Conduits," Ph.D. Dissertation, 1950 (Box-folder 3-15)
  - Technical Papers - University of Minnesota, St. Anthony Falls Hydraulic Laboratory, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 3-16)
  - Catalog of Books, 1972 (Box-folder 3-17)
  - Design Methods for Flow in Rough Conduits, 1959 (Box-folder 3-18)
  - Instructor's Supplement Answers to Problems, Applied Hydraulics in Engineering, 1963 (Box-folder 3-19)
  - Hydraulics of Energy Dissipation in Steep, Rough Channels, 1968 (Box-folder 3-20)
  - Tumbling Flow in Open Channels, 1970 (Box-folder 3-21)
  - Proceedings of the American Society of Civil Engineers, 1954 (Box-folder 3-22)
  - Highway Research Board Research Report - Culvert Hydraulics, 1953 (Box-folder 3-23)
  - Highway Research Record - Design of Culverts, Energy Dissipators, and Filter Systems, 1971 (Box-folder 3-24)
  - Scientific Communication in Geophysics, 1972 (Box-folder 3-25)
  - "Hydraulics of Energy Dissipation in Steep, Rough Channels" Report, 1967 (Box-folder 3-26)
  - Applied Hydraulics in Engineering Problem Solutions, undated (Box-folder 3-27)
  - "Effect of Boundary Roughness on Flow in Closed Conduits" MS Thesis, 1961 (Box-folder 3-28)
  - "The Forced Hydraulic Jump in Steep, Open Channels" Ph.D. Dissertation, 1971 (Box-folder 3-29)
  - Hydraulic Flow Resistance Factors for Corrugated Metal Conduits, 1970 (Box-folder 3-30)
  - Prints for A.S.C.E. Paper, 1958 (Box-folder 3-31)
  - "Hydraulic Phenomena at the Inlet Section of a Culvert" MS Thesis, 1962 (Box-folder 3-32)
  - "Hydraulic Analysis of Culverts" MS Thesis, 1960 (Box-folder 3-33)
  - "Stilling Basins for Culvert Outlets" MS Thesis, 1962 (Box-folder 3-34)
  - "Hydraulic Phenomena at Culvert Outlets" MS Thesis, 1962 (Box-folder 3-35)
  - Applied Hydraulics in Engineering, (Part 1), 1971 (Box-folder 3-36)
  - Applied Hydraulics in Engineering, (Part 2), 1971 (Box-folder 3-37)
  - Applied Hydraulics in Engineering, (Part 3), 1971 (Box-folder 4-1)
  - Applied Hydraulics in Engineerings, (Part 4), 1971 (Box-folder 4-2)
  - Advanced Hydraulics Text, (Part 1), 1958-1971 (Box-folder 4-3)
  - Advanced Hydraulics Text, (Part 2), 1958-1971 (Box-folder 4-4)
  - Requests for Tumbling Flow Bulletin, 1968-1970 (Box-folder 4-5)
  - A.S.C.E. Paper on Conduit Flow, 1953-1976 (Box-folder 4-6)
  - A.S.C.E. Paper on Tumbling Flow, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 4-7)
  - "Allowed Stresses in Redwood," Hudson Engineering Corp., 1944 (Folder 1)
- Series II: Institute for Creation Research Materials, 1994-1999
  - Acts & Facts, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 4-8)
  - Acts & Facts, 1996 (Box-folder 4-9)
  - Acts & Facts, 1997 (Box-folder 4-10)
  - Days of Praise, 1994-1996 (Box-folder 4-11)
  - Days of Praise, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 4-12)
  - Days of Praise, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 4-13)
  - Creation ex Nihilo Magazine, 1999 (Box-folder 4-14)
  - Publications Catalog, c.1990s (Box-folder 4-15)
  - Workshops and Outreach, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 4-16)